[music]
>> Nice. Excellent. Thank you very much for
being here. Super cool to see you all.
We're going to see a little bit about
what is new in FastAPI for AI. So,
first, I'm Sebastián Ramírez. You can
find me online as tiangolo. I'm from
Colombia. That's why the accent. I
created FastAPI, Typer, SQLModel, a
bunch of open source things. Now, we are
building FastAPI Cloud with a a bunch of
cool people. Some of them are around
here, some of my teammates.
Hey, we're going to talk a little bit
about FastAPI. First, let me
uh trim my context. Who has heard about
FastAPI? So, raise your hand. Nice.
Great. Who has used FastAPI?
Nice. A lot of people. That's awesome.
Then we can speedrun this first part.
Okay, so FastAPI open source framework
for building web APIs in Python. It's
been growing quite a bunch, a bunch of
GitHub stars. Right now, it has like
95K. Thing is, now Python with FastAPI
and Django has the most starred back-end
framework. So, yay, Python.
Hey, it has like around 12 million
downloads a day. So, that's a bunch of
downloads, which is like 280 million
downloads a month, which is more than
Brazil's population. Yay, kind of.
Nice.
Which is like around 10,000 downloads
since I started talking. It's a lot of
internet bytes we are consuming. It's
been growing up in the developer service
for Python, for Stack Overflow. So,
FastAPI strong. Yay. It's being used by
a bunch of companies. You might
recognize some of the logos there, or
maybe you work for one of those. It's
being used for a bunch of cool things,
like the data
the science data from the website
telescope is sent to Earth, not with
FastAPI, but then uh from Earth is
distributed around the world to all the
scientists around the world using Fast
API. They were talking about this
recently. Also, like all Open AIs like a
bunch of Fast API underneath. ChatGPT
and all just like all that stuff.
And they also use it to simulate
galaxies. And they with that they were
able in supercomputers and stuff and
they were able to discover the first
quasar. I have no idea what that means,
but it sounds super cool, so I had to
take the screenshot.
And they use it to control particle
accelerators at CERN like the Large
Hadron Collider. It sounds super scary
as well. I hope nothing breaks.
Uh so, yay Fast API.
Now, we're going to talk about what is
new in Fast API. Let's just start with a
little bit of the UX improvements for
you as users of Fast API. So, first,
let's say use pyproject.toml. You will
probably define your uh dependencies for
Fast API in a file like this. Now,
you're going to be able to declare in
the pyproject.toml where is your Fast
API application. So, whenever you run
the command line, this one Fast API dev
or Fast API run,
it's going to be able to know where is
your Fast API application without you
having to explicitly say that every
time. Uh so, here's the thing that gives
away what is happening. Let's zoom into
that a little bit. So, this is saying
this is string here that is the same
that we have here is the equivalent of
saying from backend.main import app. So,
if you have a data uh file structure
like this, so you have a backend
directory which is actually a Python
module because it's a double underscore
in it, then in it you have a main.py and
this main.py has a Fast API application.
This backend main is this from
backend.main or this backend main before
the colon, and then the app after the
colon is this one. This is what this
means. The thing is it lets you define
where is your Fast API application, so
whenever you run it, it can just like
work way easier. And then you can
integrate other tools. This is what's
actually all this was actually made by
Patrick, that is around here. I don't
see him, part of the team. So, Yay.
Next, now there's a a VS Code extension,
also Cursor extension or anti-gravity or
like a
family that you should probably use. We
just released it like 1 2 weeks ago and
people have been liking it. It's quite
cool. We just like uh
30 minutes ago reached 2,000 users on
the VS Code extension that we just
released. So, that's quite cool.
Uh I need allows you to do things like
and this was made by Savannah that is
over there. So, yay. Uh this this will
allow you to have things like this like
the path operation or endpoint, however
you call it, explorer. So, you can see
like all the endpoints or the path
operations that you define and you can
go and click each one of those and it
will take you exactly to where in the
code that path operation is. So, you can
like navigate things faster. Uh there
are the you also have like for example,
when you have tests.
This is a very simple test. Client will
get blah blah blah, get items blah blah
blah. Now you have this thing on the
top. This little ghost text, this is
called code lens. If you click it from
the test, it will take you to the code
where that endpoint or path operation
was defined. So, you're going to get
exactly where is this test uh talking
with who is this test talking to in the
code base. So, you can work more easily.
This was the VS Code extension. There's
there's a bunch of other features, but I
just wanted to highlight a couple of
things.
Now, a little bit of FastAPI for AI, not
also in terms of code itself.
First, uh let's talk about the
expectations for AI, the humanity
expectations for AI. So, yesterday I I
got into the elevator at the hotel.
There were a couple of ladies having
this very lively conversation. One was
telling to the other, "Hey, no, it's
like I'm telling you, is that Terminator
is out there." And then like, you know
like I was in the elevator and I sort of
giggled and she looked at me and she
said, "Yeah, right. Are you also coming
for the HR conference?"
And then
I look at her and said, "I come for an
AI conference."
This was the most awkward silence in an
elevator I have ever been to. You know,
like elevators are supposed to be
silent. This was silent, but it was
awkward.
And then like, you know, like before
leaving the elevator, I was trying to
make things better. So, I was trying to
explain that I actually had made this
slide. And but that didn't really help.
So, as humanity, we have these
expectations. So, we're going to have
AI. It's going to be these powerful,
scary machines that are like robots and
blah blah. And then some more people
say, "No, no, no, no. We're going to
have powerful, scary machines that are
powerful, cute machines that are like,
you know, like This This were the
expectations we had as humanity." Now,
what was the reality that we had as
humanity? Great question. What humanity
truly got
in Dutch.
And I want to delve into this. Is an AI
that helps you thrive in today's rapidly
evolving landscape? Actually, I'm sorry.
I hallucinated all that.
So, we have
uh machines. We have systems. We have,
you know, like these giant pots of
matrix multiplication systems that can
output a ton of text that in many
cases is useful. They can also output
streams of video, uh images, audio. But
in most of the cases, we are just like
using text.
The way that I tend to think about LLMs
is like is very similar to, you know,
like a
young um
white male politician.
So, if the LLM knows something and
really knows it and can like help you
with that, it will try to do it and it
will try to help it. If it doesn't know
it, in many cases, it will just make it
up and try to convince you and be super
convincing. So, the thing is like, you
know, but
So, we're getting we're getting a
ton of strings and text that in many
cases we can make useful in many
different ways. But, you know, like a
long time ago a bunch of people were
getting only ones and zeros and look all
they did with that. So, there's a lot of
stuff that we can do with this. Now, how
can we make FastAPI better for this? For
streaming data, streaming bytes. So,
that's what we are going to see. First,
and I actually don't have very fancy
slides because I spent most of the time
I had to prepare the conference to to
prepare the talk preparing the features
in FastAPI that I wanted to land before
here. So, I'm telling you things I'm
talking about things that were released
2 weeks ago or so. So, this is like all
new stuff. Your LLM models don't have
this yet into their training set.
>> [snorts]
>> First,
we need to output a bunch of text, a
bunch of stuff, a bunch of JSON. So, we
want to improve the performance for
that. The first thing is
let's say that we have an endpoint of a
FastAPI path operation like this one. We
have a Pydantic model like this.
We want to improve the performance of
the stuff that we are returning. So,
what we do
we define the return type annotation.
That's it. That's it. That's the
performance trick. Now, FastAPI has been
using this for a long while to do data
validation, to do data documentation, to
do data filtering, and data conversion
if it's necessary. Now, it's using
Pydantic and using Pydantic's core that
is built in Rust to do the data
serialization. So, you get the data
right from Python, from the memory that
is in Python, and it's converted to JSON
on the Rust side by Pydantic. So, just
by defining the return type of your path
operations, you're going to have
crazy improvement in performance, like
two weeks or something like that. It
might be that you're already doing this.
So, you just need to install the latest
version.
This also works if you have it's not
only by that equals you could have like
list of by that equals or list of ints
or dictionaries of floats or whatever.
The point is if you have the data type
in the return type is going to be used
by by that equals or by fast API to tell
by that equals hey serialize this with
JSON using your very fancy high
performance tricks. So, this is the
first thing that you can now use.
Next,
stream data. So,
when we talk about streaming, we're
normally saying we are generating a
bunch of things that we want to return
to whoever is the client and we want to
start returning that information and
give it that information to the client
even before we finish generating the
content or acquiring the content. So, we
we are taking some data and then we are
just like giving it back to the client
even before the data is finished coming.
So, you know like you're just like
passing it directly, which is very
convenient for LLMs because they just
spit tokens one at a time and you don't
want to wait and hold until you get like
everything before sending it to the
client. In many cases, not all cases,
but in many cases.
For this, a very convenient format is
JSON lines that looks like this. I'm
showing you the raw content of the HTTP
response. So, this is a JSON object that
is in one line. Then there's a new line
character, so you're just like it's a
new line and then the next one is
another JSON. Look, there are no commas,
there are no square brackets. So, this
is not really a JSON array, it's lines
of JSON.
And this means that you can send one at
a time to the user and you can actually
send infinite lines of JSON, but then
fast API will just like stream one by
one and then your client can consume one
by one. So, you are being like way
faster because you're starting to return
response so the client can start using
it very quickly and you're also saving a
bunch of memory and you might be dealing
with even infinite amounts of data. The
way that you do this in fast API
is using yield. So, this is again, this
is like released
one to weeks ago. So, when you yield it,
not only have to before you will have to
return something, now you can just yield
each one of the items. So, this is going
to yield each each item in turn. FastAPI
will know that it has to convert this
item to JSON. Again, if you define the
type annotation, FastAPI will know that
it can use Pydantic to convert each one
of these items
to a JSON line using Pydantic
underneath. So, it's like very
high-performance stuff.
Nice. In many cases, you are not dealing
just with JSON data, so you are dealing
with pure bytes. So, you can also stream
pure bytes. And the way to do it is
setting the response class to a
streaming response, and then yield each
one of the you know, like chunks of
bytes that you want to send.
And that's it. Just use yield. Before
you will be able to use a streaming
response manually,
creating a response class instance,
passing it an iterator. So, the whole
way it was quite complex. So, the idea
with this is so that you can have a very
simple code that actually does
everything that needs to do underneath.
And you can also, for example, subclass
this streaming response just to set the
media type or the content type. So, you
can say, "Okay, this is actually going
to return an image PNG." so that the
client knows what it's receiving. And
then just use those responses class, and
then just like, you know, like iterate
as normally.
Uh if this will be like if you have a
giant PNG image that you want to return,
but it will be probably way more useful
if you're returning a video or a audio
or maybe giant PDF or binary files or
something that you want to start
streaming. Or maybe it's such a large
file that you don't want to read it in
memory at all, like complete in memory
before starting to send it to the
client. So, you could use this just to
stream pure bytes.
In this case,
you are in charge of serializing and
making sure that the bytes are or actual
correct thing. FastAPI will not try to
do anything with this to convert this to
JSON or anything. No, like you're in
charge of like generating the bytes that
you want to send.
And next, the jewel of the crown,
server-sent events. So,
server-sent events are this format. It's
very similar to JSON lines, but weird.
So,
each one of these lines is one of the
events. They are separated by double new
line, which is similar to part of the
HTTP standard. And then, this is not
JSON. Look that this is Look that this
doesn't have quotes, and then it has a
colon. This is a field in the standard.
Uh data is one of the official fields.
There are like a few official fields.
Data is one of those, and then you can
pass any string here as the contents of
that data thing. In most of the cases,
the string that you want to pass is just
JSON. In most of the cases, you will be
still like just sending JSON. But you
pass it inside of this particular data
format. The thing with server-sent
events is browsers have an included API
for reading server-sent events when you
send when you request them using a get
request. So, browsers have a way to just
consume these server-sent events.
If
If you don't use like the the default
APIs from the browser, you can also use
it with just like regular fetch or like
whatever, but then you are in charge of
parsing this specific format.
And the way that you do this in FastAPI
is that you set the response class to an
event source response.
And then you yield items.
FastAPI will make sure that each one of
these items to JSON and is that is put
in the right place.
There are also a bunch of things that
need to be had in mind when using
server-sent events. You should be
sending uh
You should be sending a ping comment, so
there's a way to not only send data, but
you can also send a comment. You can
also set an ID for the event so that the
client can say, "The last event that I
received was uh this ID." And then that
you can restart from that. You can send
a retry. You can send the
There are like a few other fields that
you can set.
So, uh by the standard it's suggested
that you will send a ping every 15
seconds so that they, you know, like
proxies and things don't cut the
connection. FastAPI does that underneath
by default. So, it will handle
everything by default, set the proper
classes,
uh the proper
headers, HTTP headers to prevent some
proxies from buffering stuff. Like, you
know, like there's a few things,
a couple of things that need to be done
so that this all works properly.
Also,
the browsers only support get, but for
example, uh MCP, uh at least the latest
versions, uh supports server-sent events
with POST requests. It will work the
same. In FastAPI, you just like set
app.get or app.post, whatever, response
class EventSourceResponse, and then you
yield each one of the items. It's a bit
weird that it's server-sent events, and
then you have an EventSourceResponse,
and each one of these is an event, and
this whole thing is an event stream. So,
it's like, let's have like a thousand
terms for the same technology and put
them all together. But in the end, it's
just the same thing.
Uh and then, if you define the type
annotation for what is is what what is
what is each one, I forgot to English.
What is each one of the items that
you're returning with Pydantic, then
it's also going to be used to serialize
the thing in the Rust side.
Now, if you want to have more control
and select each one of the other fields,
you can also do that. You can set the
specific data that you want to send, but
you can also say like, this is an event
of type blah. The default event is
message, that's what you will normally
use, but if you have a very fancy
server-sent events system set up that
needs to send other types of events, you
can also configure this manually here.
You can set the ID, and you can set the
retry. You can also send even a
comments, that is like, you know, part
of the standard. So, if you have more
you want to have more control over the
server-sent event
standard, you can also do that as well.
And if you want to send a I, you know,
like use pure strings, You want to
serialize the things the way that you
want without FastAPI trying to convert
it to JSON, you can just use raw data.
So, this will just send each one of
these lines directly as they are.
Now, a little bit of FastAPI for AI and
skills.
FastAPI now includes a bundle skill. The
official skill of FastAPI comes with
FastAPI. Whenever there's a new version
of FastAPI, this skill is updated. Like
I updated it so that it has like the
information to use all these new
features. So, if you have FastAPI
installed
and you can see this is part of the
repository. If you check in the files
that are installed, you're going to have
the skill right there with telling the
the agent how to use all these new
features that are not even in the in the
training set. We are also working on
setting up the tool so that you can just
like have this installed and updated
automatically inside of your system. I'm
also trying to convince the agent
providers or hiring necessities because
we keep making up words
to just like support this. Because the
idea is that the libraries should be
able to provide their own official
skills that are like constantly up to
date. But this is already, you know,
like this already shipped. It's already
bundled there. It's already
there. You can just like sim link while
we finish setting up the the skill
tools.
Now, I wanted to show you a quick demo.
Let's see if we have enough time. So, I
want to show you how to use this server
sentiment things. Things. So, we are
using a a Pydantic AI
agent. This is a very simple agent. You
don't have to read the prompt.
And then we have a bunch of Pydantic
models because as a wise man once said,
Pydantic is all you need.
Then
we have we are saying, "Okay,
we're going to receive some messages.
So, this is regular Pydantic. We are
again using the thing that I was telling
you of defining what is the return type.
We are just saving this to Redis.
And you know, to we are just like using
what what you would expect. And then we
are defining the event source response.
So this is a server sent event stream
thing.
And we are just yielding each one of the
messages that is processed. So
this will receive messages that we sent,
will process them,
we will send them and save them in
Redis. Then with Pydantic AI is going to
process them and generate more stuff and
like generate the actual final amazing
result that we want to have. It's going
to save it on Redis and then from here
we just going to start it and we're
going to just going to send it. And then
like we also define the type of the
data.
Now this is the point where I have to
show you the actual code.
Okay, so this is the code that we have
here. This is the moment of the live
demo and I have very bad signal so this
is probably going to break.
>> [snorts]
>> But I wanted to show you this live so
I'm going to deploy it. Fast API deploy.
Eh.
And I don't know if I have good signal
so
we'll see.
Okay, yeah, this is deploying.
We [snorts] find the deployment. And
also this is also I wanted to show you
the VS Code extension. So here it is. I
can see I was telling you that we have a
post thing to send the messages so we
can see the messages here. We can also
see where we are streaming the messages
all this stuff and we can also deploy
this with the CLI.
And I was just saying it was before. Oh,
this is this signed out automatically.
Well, I'm not going to show you that.
But this is what I wanted to show you
the demo using server sent events.
It loads. Yes, it loads. So now I can
say okay, I'm Sebastian.
And I'm going to say hello SF.
>> [snorts]
>> That's my post on LinkedIn influencer
and now it's just like link identifying
it.
And now
>> [laughter]
>> yeah.
Am I hiring? Am I vibe coding? I don't
know. Now yes, we are hiring more.
William in chicken to the happy funny.
You believe in chicken. Okay, you can
just scan it and just see it and it's
just going to keep rolling on your
phones. You can do it right now. That
was the intention and I was expecting to
handle whatever questions we had just as
this.
So,
we will have to have like LinkedIn
questions.
Hey, I will hope you will fill more
stuff there. Also, this this is actually
deployed on Fast API Cloud. If you join
the waiting list with this link, we have
more stuff there.
It's already pre-filled with a code so
that you can skip. We have several
thousand waiting list, but if you join
with that link with the Pi AI code, we
will let you in this or next week if you
join today.
So, yeah.
What's next for Fast API and AI? As I
reflect on my journey, I can help but
ponder the intersection of Fast API and
AI. Let that sink in. I think like that
seagull is mocking me. Okay, anyway,
that's what I have for you. Let's
I don't know if we even have time for
questions.
Sorry, we don't have time for questions.
So, you can ask me around if you want.
Thank you very much everyone.
>> [applause]
[music]